בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is סמך גימל Samech Gimmel
63, we pick up at the bottom of the very bottom of
סמך בית עמוד בית, Samech Bais Amud Bais, and we are talking
about the issue of שלא לאוכליו, shelo l'ochlav,
and we start with a you know shechting it for the sake
of people that might be the owners but are not able to
eat, which is a special פסול pasul by an invalidity by קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach and applies only at the time of שחיטה. shechitah.
And we start, we resume that four lines from the bottom, תניא.
Tanya.
תניא, Tanya, אחרים אומרים, acherim omrim, others say which is usually רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, understood to be רב מאיר: Reb Meir: הקדים מולים
לערלים כשר, hikdim mulim l'arelim kasher, ערלים למולים פסול. arelim l'mulim pasul.
So here's interesting: if you first say I'm shechting it for מולים
mulim and ערלים, arelim, then it's כשר, kasher, you said the good
one first. If you say I'm shechting it for ערלים arelim and
מולים, mulim, you said the bad one first, it's invalid. The גמרא
Gemara now is going to work till the next משנה mishna till
the משנה mishna to unpack this. So the גמרא Gemara says: מאי
שנא מולים לערלים דכשר, mai shna mulim l'arelim de-kasher, why would you
say מולים mulim and ערלים arelim is a כשר? kasher? דכולה ערלה
בעינן וליכא, dekula orla ba'inan ve-leka, because we have been saying for
the last few days that as opposed to שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah,
when it comes to שלא לאוכליו, shelo l'ochlav, thank you, it's only
invalid if everyone, if you're thinking about an entire invalid group. So
when you say מולים mulim and ערלים, arelim, it's not invalid because
some of them are מולים, mulim, and therefore that's not an invalid
thought at the time of שחיטה. shechitah. ערלים למולים נמי, arelim l'mulim
nami, so even if you said the words in a different order,
nevertheless דכולה ערלה בעינן וליכא, dekula orla ba'inan ve-leka, you're referring to
a group that's a mixed group, it should not be a problem.
So what what is the difference? Top of סמך גימל עמוד אלף:
Samech Gimmel Amud Aleph: לימא קסברי אחרים, leima kasavri acherim, maybe here's
what they hold: אינה לשחיטה אלא לבסוף, eina lishchitah ela besof, וכדרבא
דאמר רבא, u-kh'de-Rava d'amar Rava, עדיין היא מחלוקת. adayin hi machloket. So
in those two words like an enormous amount of information is
packed. Like you know, sometimes the גמרא Gemara like I think I
don't know if you felt it yesterday, but even without the אגדתא
aggadata it like you know spells out at great length its argument.
Here it's packing an entire סוגיא sugya into like four or six
words. So there are two סוגיות. sugyot. One is a discussion of
ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף yeshna lishchitah mitchilah v'ad sof or אינה
לשחיטה אלא לבסוף. eina lishchitah ela l'besof. Is the act of שחיטה
shechitah considered to have been done when you finish or is it
considered to be have been, you know, are you doing the act
of שחיטה shechitah all along the way? The relevance of that can
be applied in many different cases.
One example would be, I mean, you know, you can't say the
whole act is at the end because then you're shechting an animal
that's already a טריפה. treifah. But still, right, because if at the
last moment the animal already has part of its, you know, of
its trachea and esophagus cut. But nevertheless, it's whether you sort of
say that the act takes effect at the end or would you
say the whole process is defined as as the act?
Like on a כלי, kli, at what point in the manufacture of
a כלי kli is it susceptible to טומאה? tumah?
Um,
yes, but that's a...
whether you're near the end of the process or at the very...
No, no, the difference here is, no, the question is not which
point is it שחיטה, shechitah, but the question is whether more it's
a whether it's a discrete point in time or whether it's a
process. That's really the question. Do we look at שחיטה shechitah as
a process? So from the and therefore it's the entire from the
time you begin till the time you end or do we look
at שחיטה shechitah at the at a discrete point and we said
you did שחיטה shechitah when you finished? That that's the question. Whether
we look at it as an act or a process if you
want to say it that way or a moment or a discrete
point or a process. So very often the relevance for this there
could be a lot of different issues. If I'm shechting an animal
for עבודה זרה avodah zarah and I have a thought of עבודה
זרה avodah zarah at the beginning but not at the end. But
you know different types of ways in which this in this in
which this question comes up. It comes up a lot in discussions
about a invalidating thought for קרבנות. korbanot. Now nobody suggests that if
I have a thought when I'm beginning the שחיטה shechitah I'm doing
it with פסולים, psulim, you know, I'm doing it שלא לשמה shelo
lishmah and then but I don't think that at the moment I
finish nobody says oh okay I'm off because I wasn't thinking it
at that exact moment. The difference is though that again because everybody
agrees it's like even if it's at that last discrete point it
incorporates everything that came before. So the issue is though when did
that thought take effect? If I'm thinking I'm doing it שלא לשמה
shelo lishmah does it take effect now because I'm doing a שחיטה
shechitah now so it took effect now? Or do we say no
no no the שחיטה shechitah isn't finished yet when I finish then
that last discrete point will incorporate everything that came before and it'll
take effect at that last moment? Okay so this is the issue
of I know that's pretty abstract I'll tie it in here to
help to make sense of it. Of ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף
yeshna lishchitah mitchilah v'ad sof or not. So in terms of this
question of ערלים arelim and מולים mulim here's the issue let me
sort of
maybe lay it out like to describe it graphically okay.
Here's where you start your שחיטה shechitah
right here there the two there the trachea and the esophagus will
be whole okay and here's where you end your שחיטה shechitah okay
the knife has now finished cutting through that okay really graphic. Okay
here's where you
here's where you end it okay. So, if we say ישנו לשחיטה
מתחילה ועד סוף, yeshno lishchita mitchila ve'ad sof, right? Which is, right?
Then you're thinking here, so you think at one point מולים, mulim,
and then as you're continuing to שחט, shecht, you think
ערלים, areilim, okay?
Or the reverse. Right?
Let's, well, the גמרא Gemara actually is going to get to articulating
it in a minute and be very clear that we're talking about
articulating it. So we'll do it like this way. You do ערלים
areilim and then you do מולים. mulim. Okay? Something like that. So,
since all of this, if you say ישנו לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף,
yeshno lishchita mitchila ve'ad sof, this entire process was considered שחיטה. shechita.
So during שחיטה, shechita, you had an ערלים areilim thought and then
a split second later you had a מולים mulim thought. So you
were thinking of both. So since you're thinking of both, so we
say if you have a mixed thought like ערלים areilim and מולים,
mulim, it's כשר. kasher. So if you say ישנו לשחיטה מתחילה ועד
סוף, yeshno lishchita mitchila ve'ad sof, it would be... it would be
כשר. kasher. However, if you say אינו לשחיטה אלא בסוף, eino lishchita
ela basof, you would think the same thing. At this one point,
we assess what your thoughts were and you had both of those
thoughts, we would also think it's כשר, kasher, right? What's the difference?
No, but there was more at the end.
But, but you might remember that there's another debate about whether בתחילת
דבריו אדם נתפס, batchilat devarav adam nitpas, right? Or בסוף דבריו אדם
נתפס. besof devarav adam nitpas. Whether, if you say a statement that
takes effect immediately, not over time but immediately, if I say this
animal is an עולה שלמים, olah-shelamim, right? Or right, so is it
some type of a hybrid or do we say עולה שלמים olah-shelamim
are somehow contradictory ideas and we'll only focus on the first one?
Okay? And there's the position of רבי יוסי Reb Yossi that says
בתחילת דבריו אדם נתפס. batchilat devarav adam nitpas. So therefore, in this
case, if you say if these are at discrete points, so they're
separate... they're separate things that you said. But if you say אינו
לשחיטה אלא בסוף, eino lishchita ela basof, so then at that last
moment it's like you said at once, you know, at the same
second ערלים areilim and מולים. mulim. If you say we go by
the first part of a somewhat contradictory statement, though why this is
seen as a contradictory statement's not clear because it could be a
mixed group. Anyway, then you would be caught by the ערלים. areilim.
So it's... so... so let's read that again inside. I know this
is a little confusing.
I mean I've never done שחיטה shechita or even observed it, but
it seems like a pretty quick act.
Yeah, I'm sure it takes less than a second. So you have
to like, you know, really micro-divide it. Okay. לימא קסבר אחרים אינו
לשחיטה אלא בסוף, leima kasavar Achereim eino lishchita ela basof, so everything
takes place, everything that happened until that moment is incorporated, I'll say
it that way, in the last moment.
וכדרבה דאמר רבה עדיין היא מחלוקת. uchderabbah de'amar Rabbah adayin hi machloket.
Like now רבה Rabbah says that it's still a debate, meaning this
is a whole other סוגיא. sugya. But the question is the debate
of whether you say,
you know, בתחילת דבריו אדם נתפס batchilat devarav adam nitpas or בסוף
דבריו אדם נתפס. besof devarav adam nitpas. There's a debate whether... would
רבי מאיר Reb Meir say it when it all takes place at
the same moment. Because normally, okay, normally if I say, like I
said to you before, הרי זו עולה שלמים, harei zu olah-shelamim, alright?
Now, if you're listening to me, you could say, well, maybe he
meant to say עולה olah and then he changed his mind afterwards
and said שלמים, shelamim, so we'll ignore the second part of what
I said because it's clear that I... maybe I only wanted to...
maybe I really only wanted the עולה. olah. Maybe that's the logic
of רבי מאיר. Reb Meir. When I said שלמים shelamim afterwards I
changed my mind and it's too late to change your mind. So
the גמרא Gemara asks in another סוגיא, sugya, what if I said
it like the following way: At noon today, I want this animal
to be an עולה-שלמים. olah-shelamim. Okay, so you can't say that I
changed my mind because I'm sort of referring to a later point.
It's not like it first happened and then I had a second
thought, and I want some hybrid at that point to take effect.
So אביי Abaye says, "Oh, in that case רבי מאיר Reb Meir
would agree it's a hybrid statement." Not רבי מאיר, Reb Meir, רבי
יוסי. Reb Yossi. And רבה Rabbah says, עדיין היא מחלוקת. adayin hi
machloket. No, even if you push it off to a later time
and you say you want it to happen together, according to רבי
יוסי, Reb Yossi, the first only the first part happens, only the
עולה olah happens. So this is how the גמרא Gemara understands what's
happening here. You're doing a שחיטה, shechita, you're saying ערלים areilim and
מולים, mulim, the effect is that they both happen together at the
end. So there's a reason to say that, oh, then we wouldn't
say בתחילת דבריו. batchilat devarav. It's all happening together at the end
at one moment and it's a hybrid. But that's why no, רבה
Rabbah says עדיין היא מחלוקת. adayin hi machloket. This issue of בתחילת
דבריו אדם נתפס batchilat devarav adam nitpas is still debated, meaning the
person would still say even when it all happens at a later
time and it combines things you said, we still go only by
the first part. So that's how the גמרא Gemara is explaining an
ערלים-מולים areilim-mulim statement becomes only the first part of what you said.
If it was the שחיטה shechita throughout, then each part would have
a separate point in time to take effect and therefore it would
be mixed. If it's at the end, they both take effect together
and if you say that when they take effect together we only
look at the first part, then the statement becomes based on the
first thing that you said. So let's read that inside. הלכך הקדים
מולים לערלים, hilcha hikdim mulim le'areilim, if you said מולים mulim first,
מולים חיילי ערלים לא חיילי mulim cheili areilim lo cheili at that
last moment when only the first part of your statement. מולים, moolim,
and not ערלים areilim and it's good. היכא דאמר ערלים למולים, heicha
d'amar areilim l'moolim, if you said the opposite order, ערלים חיילי מולים
לא חיילי. areilim chaili moolim lo chaili. ערלים Areilim takes effect, not
מולים moolim because again it's not a mixed statement. Since it's all
happening at one second, only then and it's only the first part
of it takes effect according to רבי יוסי Reb Yosi that this
would be going like it says בתחילת דבריו אדם נתפס. b'tchilas d'varav
adam nitpas. חיילי Chaili is like חל. chal. חל, Chal, takes effect.
אמר רבה, Amar Rabba, said רבה, Rabba, or some have the גרסא
girsa of רבא Rava who says the previous one. Previous was רבה,
Rabba, so some
switch I guess the
רבא Rava and the רבה. Rabba. Okay, so we'll have it this
way. אמר רבה, Amar Rabba, so says רבה Rabba because רבה Rabba
can't be responding to רבא Rava because רבא Rava was earlier. Anyway,
לא, lo, לעולם קסבר אחרים ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף. le'olam kasavar
acharin yeshna lishchita mit'tchila v'ad sof. No, that's not its true. You
could say the שחיטה shchita is considered throughout the process, it's considered
the act of שחיטה. shchita. And therefore it's a mixed statement. It's
a mixed statement, ערלים areilim and מולים, moolim, it should be good.
So what's the difference which order you did it? דהכא במאי עסקינן
dehacha b'mai askinan דגמר בלבו לתרוייהו, degamar belivo l'travaiyu, in your heart,
we would say in your head, anyway in your heart you're thinking
both, מולים moolim and ערלים, areilim, והוציא בפיו לערלים, vehotzi b'piv l'areilim,
but what you actually said was only ערלים. areilim. You didn't say
both, okay, in the first, in the scenario where it's no good.
The scenario where it is good you said מולים moolim and you
didn't say ערלים, areilim, then obviously it's okay. Okay, ולא הספיק לומר
למולים, vlo hispik lomar l'moolim, you didn't say the second part of
your sentence, עד שנגמרה שחיטה, ad shenigmara shchita, until you actually finished.
So here you are, you're shechting, you're thinking מולים ערלים, moolim areilim,
you think I'm going to say למולים ולערלים, l'moolim v'l'areilim, and then
you actually begin saying למולים ולערלים. l'moolim v'l'areilim. But here's why it
matters which you said first because you only got out the words
למולים l'moolim here, then you finished your שחיטה, shchita, and then you
got out the words ולערלים. u'l'areilim. Okay, so that key line, only
half of what you were thinking got said at the critical moment.
The other half got said after. That's case number one, that's good
because at the critical moment you said למולים. l'moolim. If you were
to say nothing is good, if you say למולים. l'moolim. Case number
two is you reversed the order. You said לערלים, l'areilim, then the
שחיטה shchita was done and then you said ולמולים. u'l'moolim. So what
you said after doesn't help. What only matters is what you said
during. So the reason the order matters is really because you only
got one of them out of your mouth while it was the
critical time. And the whole position מחשבה ודיבור מתחילה ועד סוף. machshava
v'dibbur mi'tchila v'ad sof. Right, well the issue about דיבור dibbur we're
going to, so that we're going to get to in a minute.
So let's see as the גמרא Gemara spells this out because, because
it challenges this whole notion of תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur
and you know and how it's like. Right, you bundle together what
you're saying or you bundle the idea that
you're in the middle of a sentence and. Right. Yeah, that's a
very good question.
You know normally we say that like, you know תוך כדי דיבור
toch k'dei dibbur you can reverse yourself.
A lot of this has to do with the fact that normal
תוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur is when דיבור dibbur
is
a reflection of what you're thinking and it's not a,
I'm trying to sort of like performative act in itself.
Okay, whereas when you say let's take a simpler example, not the
case here. When I'm מקדיש makdish this קרבן korban and I say
it's an עולה שלמים. olah shlamim. It's not just I'm giving expressions
to what I'm thinking, but the words עולה olah are transforming it
into an עולה. olah. So then you could sort of say well
as soon as you said that somehow you know that took effect
immediately. Whereas if we're trying to assess what you're thinking, you know
maybe we can step back and look at the bigger picture. Although
here when we talk about it as what as a thought by
the קרבן, korban, it does seem to be that even if we
require speech and this has been the issue we've been discussing when
you say שלא לשמה shelo lishma is it just what you think
or do we require speech? You would have assumed we require speech
as a reflection as of what you're thinking, not as a performative
act. And therefore I think that that is an excellent question. By
the קרבן korban I can understand it better because as soon as
the words are out of your mouth they take effect. But if
it's in sense of assessing state of mind and תוך כדי דיבור
toch k'dei dibbur and we sort of you know but you're right
in other cases as well even when it's a performative act we
sometimes look at תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur. Let's say I'm
making a ברכה, bracha, right? בורא פרי העץ, borei pri ha'eitz, בורא
פרי האדמה, borei pri ha'adama, right? Or something like that. That's also
a performative act and I get to correct it תוך כדי דיבור.
toch k'dei dibbur. So yeah I mean it's an excellent question.
To me I meant to say ah this is
an עולה olah I meant שלמים. shlamim. Yeah. Well that's also an
interesting question if you know and that gets I think partly to
this issue as well if it's a טעות to'os as opposed to
a non-טעות. to'os. Right? If you are not there's a difference between
נמלך nimlach which is you changed your mind. You said עולה שלמים
olah shlamim you changed your mind, too late to change your mind.
Whereas you said עולה olah oh I meant to say שלמים, shlamim,
right? That that might that actually might be open for the תוך
כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur because that's a correction. All right. So
but it is a good point that we are we are rarely
so sort of. too bad you already said it, too late type
of a thing and here we are. But part of it is
I think the combination of the fact that it's a performative act
and b, although that's not so true by the שלא לשמה, shelo
lishma, and b, as Michael points out, the difference between changing your
mind or correcting what you said. Okay, I want to actually refer
to both the that issue in a second as when we finish
the
סיפא.
seifa. If I said ערלים arelim and oops, I meant to
say מולים, mulim, yeah, but I already שחט, shachat, that wouldn't make
a difference because it was after I finished the שחיטה. shechita. Right,
it could be that. Although I will say that there is a
place where תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur in the גמרא Gemara
actually can work something out even, meaning have an impact even if
it's after the critical act. There's, I mean, it's one of the
more difficult applications of תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, but the
גמרא Gemara says if somebody heard that their father dies and they
tear קריעה, keriah, and then תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur they
hear that their mother dies, יוצא קריעה yotzei keriah for their mother
because it was תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, right? Which is
bizarre. Normally you think the whole point of קריעה keriah is in
reaction to, you know, not in the context of, and but normally,
yes, to say, you know, to that that without putting that גמרא
Gemara aside, to say תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur won't work
after some critical cutoff point, you know, after it's no longer the
זמן, zman, that's what the גמרא Gemara here is saying. Yes, Rivka.
I just want to point out this is a group, right? So
it's not signing on as individuals. Right. They're signing on intending to
be part of a group.
Right. And here we are, we are the כהן kohen is deciding.
Well, it's a good point that you mention, which is is that
the irony about the whole thing is is that the פסול psul
of שלא לאוכליו shelo l'ochlav is a group that's already been created.
We already have this group. Some people, you know, maybe don't belong
in the group or maybe after the group was created, they became
sick or they became טמא, tamei, but right now, right, this group
is the owners. It's just that some of them can't eat. And
actually, but rather than making it invalid because the group is a
bad group, right, we're making it invalid based on what the guy
the כהן kohen is thinking when he's doing the שחיטה. shechita.
So he is dividing up the group.
He's not viewing
them as a group.
Right. The beauty of it is is that when he does view
them as a group and it's a mixed group, the fact that
then it's כשר, kasher, but when he divides them and focuses only
on the פסולין, psulin, that's when it becomes invalid. That's exactly how
the invalidity is created. Right. We can say the objective reality is
otherwise. I understand. I understand.
But like a corporation.
Yeah, but you could say the same about שלא לשמה. shelo lishma.
They want they sanctify it as a פסח. pesach. This כהן kohen
is thinking that it's a שלמים shlamim and he's going to invalidate.
That's the problem of these פסולי מחשבה's, psulei machshava you're giving it
over to the hands of the כהן. kohen. Okay, let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says with this. So the issue here of order
is what you said at the critical time. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: ובהא פליגי. u'beha pligi. So what's the debate? Right?
Meaning it seems like this is the position of רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, not everybody would agree with this. It seems like it's a
reasonable position, I mean, you only it's what you said at the
critical time. No. ובהא פליגי. u'beha pligi. דרבי מאיר סבר לא בעינן
פיו ולבו שווים. deRabbi Meir savar lo ba'inan piv v'libo shavin. רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir said,
I don't care if what you said, what matters what you said
is the first thing you said, and this gets also to what
Dov was talking about, is not what you were thinking. You okay?
And so it's you said it, you said it. That's what you
go by. So it's the first part you said, that's the critical
moment, whether it was what you were intending or not, it's what
you said. רבנן סברי בעינן פיו ולבו שווים. Rabbanan savri ba'inan piv
v'libo shavin. I'm sorry,
speech only matters if it's reflecting what you're thinking. And since you
were thinking a mixed thought and that's an and that's acceptable, even
if only the word you said at the critical time were the
wrong ones, it doesn't matter, it's not going to trap you. Okay,
now, I want to say an important point, which is here is
the we've been saying all along, you know, that שלא לשמה shelo
lishma and שלא לשם בעלים shelo l'shem ba'alim and שלא לאוכליו shelo
l'ochlav is what you're thinking. But here the גמרא Gemara says it's
what you said. The only issue is does it matter if it
matches what you're thinking, but nobody is saying ignore what you said,
it's all about what you were it's all about what you were
thinking, right? Here sounds clear like no, it's all about what you
said, but do we sort of throw it out if it's not
the same as what you were thinking? So רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot both say from here we see that when the גמרא Gemara
talks about פיגול pigul or שלא לשמה shelo lishma and all these
things which have got invalid thoughts, it really means that it's what
you're saying, invalid articulated thoughts, not just invalid thoughts in your head.
So for example, if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says,
the long רש"י? Rashi? No, not the long one. רש"י Rashi says,
no, the one right before that, about eight lines, six lines down
in the medium-sized line, והכא במאי עסקינן, ve-hacha bemai askinan, the first
line and the word is
עסקינן, askinan, דתני הקדים ערלים למולים פסול כגון שגמר בליבו להוציא מולים
אחריהם ולומר ערלים ומולים. detani hikdim arelim le-mulim pasul k'gon she-gamar belibo
le-hotzi mulim achreihem velomar arelim umulim. כל מחשבה דקדשים מוציא בפיו. kol
machshava de-kodshim motzi befiv. Nice little important little point.
Anytime we talk about thinking, it means what you're saying, right? And
look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says same point, דרבי מאיר סבר
לא
בעינן פיו ולבו שווים,
deRabbi Meir savar lo ba'inan
piv v'libo shavin, מכאן דקדקו,
mikan dikdeku, דהא דקרי בכל דוכתא פיגול פסול מחשבה,
de-ha de-kari bechol douchta pigul psul
machshava, לאו דווקא דאינו פיגול עד שיוציא בפיו. lav davka de-eino pigul
ad she-yotzi befiv. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So the reason they say that
is because the גמרא, Gemara, even when it says what you said
doesn't matter, is because it didn't match what you were thinking and
then therefore we can dismiss it, not because you go by what
you were thinking. Okay, so that's the issue. You said only half
or it only mattered the half because that was when you were
doing the שחיטה. shechita. Do we go by what you said or
do we say in the end it wasn't what you were thinking
so we throw it out? Okay, and that's the issue. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, וכסבר רבי מאיר לא מפיו ולבו
שוין? Vecasavar Rabbi Meir lo mipiv uleevo shavin? Does רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir really say you don't need what you say to match what
you're thinking and you go by what you said even if it
doesn't match what you're thinking? ורמינהו, Veraminehu, I'll ask you on this:
המכוין לומר תרומה ואמר מעשר מעשר ואמר תרומה, Hamiskavein lomar trumah ve-amar
maaser maaser ve-amar trumah, you mistakenly said something you weren't thinking. או
שאיני נכנס לבית זה, O she-eini nichnas labayis zeh, you made a
נדר, neder, I'm not going to go into that house, ואמר לזה,
ve-amar lazeh, and you meant to say another house. שאיני נהנה לזה,
She-eini ne-eneh lazeh, or I won't derive benefit from this guy, ואמר
לזה, ve-amar lazeh, and you accidentally you said another guy. לא אמר
כלום, Lo amar klum, that is not a—that does not take effect,
any of those, that נדר neder or that תרומה trumah or that
מעשר, maaser, עד שיהיו פיו ולבו שוין, ad sheyehei piv uleevo shavin,
until your mouth and your heart are the same. So that's a
universal principle that your speech, if it's not matching what you're thinking,
is dismissed. So therefore that should be true here as well. So
the גמרא Gemara says, now by the way that issue could depend
on to what degree you're thinking about something as a speech act
and to what degree you're thinking about something as an articulation of
thought, right? So if it's a speech act, right, then maybe it
wouldn't matter as much what you're thinking and maybe different areas would
have different—would be different about that. But if anything, the issue of
קרבנות korbanos is certainly the one where it's most to be understood
as an expression, an articulation of thought, and therefore we would need
פיו ולבו שוין. piv uleevo shavin. Other things like a נדר, neder,
right, could be seen more as a type of a speech act
that it that creates a certain reality.
And certainly, it's almost a קל וחומר kal vachomer what the גמרא
Gemara is saying. If by a נדר neder and so on you
need פיו ולבו שוין, piv uleevo shavin, how much more so here?
So that was a very interesting and creative answer which really also
got us to thinking about the relationship between speech and thought in
this act. But the גמרא Gemara in the end rejects it, says
even—that you need it to match what you're thinking, and since it
didn't match what you're thinking, we throw it out. אלא אמר אביי,
Ela amar Abaye, rather אביי Abaye says, רישא דאמר סימן ראשון למולין
וסימן שני אף לערלין. Reisha de-amar siman rishon lemulin vesiman sheini af
lareilin. Here's the difference. Here's what—here's why it matters the order. When
you're שוחט, shechting, you first say—when you שוחט shecht the trachea, you
say I'm doing it למולין. lemulin. And when you שוחט shecht the
esophagus, you say אף לערלין. af lareilin. So therefore when you said
the words אף לערלין, af lareilin, that meant when you said אף
לערלין, af lareilin, it already had מולין mulin incorporated into it because
you started with מולין. mulin. דבסימן שני, Devesiman sheini, so now when
you were שוחט shechting the second סימן, siman, right, נמי פתיחי ביה
מולין, nami ptichi be-mulin, the מולין mulin is sort of interspersed in
it, so it's a mixed thought. סיפא דאמר סימן ראשון לערלין סימן
שני למולין—now Seifa de-amar siman rishon lareilin siman sheini lemulin when you
reversed the order, that's when it matters. Because when you שוחט shechted
the first סימן, siman, you said לערלין, lareilin, סימן שני למולין, siman
sheini lemulin, and the second one you said למולין. lemulin. So therefore
the למולין lemulin of the second might incorporate the לערלין, lareilin, but
it doesn't matter, the לערלין lareilin stands by itself. דבסימן ראשון הלא
לא פתיחי ביה מולין, Devesiman rishon halo ptichi be-mulin, the first—the first
סימן siman you're שוחט shechting was just לערלין lareilin by itself. ורבי
מאיר לטעמיה דאמר מפלגין בחצי מתיר ורבנן לטעמיה דאמרי אין מפלגין בחצי
מתיר. Verabbi Meir letaimei de-amar mefalgin be-chatzi matir verabbanan letaimei de-amri ein
mefalgin be-chatzi matir. So
again, in this גמרא Gemara in like single lines you have enormous
סוגיות sugyas in ש"ס, Shas, right? פיו ולבו שוין, piv uleevo shavin,
you know, יש לו שחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף, yesh lo shechita mitechila
ve-ad sof, and now we have the idea מפלגין בחצי מתיר. mefalgin
be-chatzi matir. Can you make פיגול pigul with half of a מתיר?
matir? Meaning there are two things which make it a good שחיטה:
shechita: the trachea and the esophagus. If you have a פיגול pigul
thought with only the one of them, does that create פיגול, pigul,
or does it have to be with the entire? Now, it's funny
because to some degree that sounds like the יש לו שחיטה מתחילה
ועד סוף yesh lo shechita mitechila ve-ad sof question, right? But anyway,
they seem to be related, but that's how the גמרא Gemara is
framing this here. And it says the basic answer is: if you
start with לערלין lareilin and that was when you did the—fully did
the trachea, then according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and it stands
by itself, it wasn't preceded with מולין mulin that מולין mulin could
then create the context and it means mixed—it stood by itself and
it came first and it said לערלין, lareilin, that—that creates a פסול
מחשבה psul machshava the same way it would create פיגול. pigul. And
the rabbis say no, you only look at it when both are
cut and then you have both statements there and then it's a
mixed thought.
So it's—מפלגין בחצי מתיר mefalgin be-chatzi matir also applies across the board.
Right, so—right, so מפלגין בחצי מתיר mefalgin be-chatzi matir would be like
by, you know, like the—right, there's the לבונה levonah and the—when by
a מנחה mincha when you do
the—there's both, you know, you have to be מקטיר maktir both the
לבונה levonah and the קומץ kometz of the מנחה, mincha, and what
if you had a פיגול pigul thought by only one of those?
So yes, that is—yeah, one is רישא reisha and another is סיפא.
seifa. Right, although by זריקה zrika there's you never need two, even
for a חטאת chatas בדיעבד b'dieved one you're יוצא, yotzei, so I
don't I don't think it applies to the different זריקות zrikos by
the חטאת. chatas. But anyway, but yeah, you're correct, it's a more
larger debate. Okay, but it would seem to get at this case
to a question of right, there's something similar about the question of
does what you're thinking at one stage already sort of have an
effect yet or not? But Dov was absolutely correct, it's a different,
it's a larger debate. Okay.
Yeah, if you say something like ערל ומולים. arel u'mulim. What? You
know, if you say something like ערל ומולים. arel u'mulim.
So right, we discussed that, I don't know, if you're thinking about
the people and you say למולים lamulim and nobody in the group
happens to be—I mean you say לערלים larelim and nobody in the
group happens to be an ערל. arel. Or let's say you said
ראובן ושמעון, Reuven u'Shimon, and you didn't know that שמעון Shimon happened
to be an ערל. arel. Like exactly what this means, I, you
know, what it means to say לערלים larelim is a good question.
I don't know, it only applies to the world of קרבנות. korbanot.
Right, and another kind of play to different fruits and I say
בורא פרי העץ borei pri ha'etz and I was only thinking about
two of them out of let's say four of them.
No, no, it's specifically מתיר matir on
the two that I was thinking.
Right, it's specifically מתיר matir and it's specifically the idea that there
are two discrete acts that make this a valid קרבן korban or
make this a valid עבודה, avodah, and your bad thought was on
one of those discrete acts. So but again, it is, you know,
so I do think it intersects with the issues of ישנה לשחיטה
מתחילה ועד סוף yeshna l'shechita mitechila v'ad sofa because why do you
think about שחיטה shechita as two discrete acts? Why don't you think
about שחיטה shechita as one act? You know, I mean the very
fact that you're dividing them into two discrete acts sort of suggests
the ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף yeshna l'shechita mitechila v'ad sofa idea.
But Dov was absolutely correct that it applies to other things as
well. I want to just end this discussion because it is fascinating
about this idea of thought and speech by looking quickly at a
short תוספות Tosafot where he says, המכוון לומר תרומה hamiskaven lomar trumah
where the גמרא gemara says, oh פיו ולבו שוין piv v'libo shavin
you need to have that. תוספות: Tosafot: אפילו דברים שבלב לא היו
דברים. afilu devarim shebalev lo hayu devarim. What ever happened to the
idea דברים שבלב אינם דברים? devarim shebalev einam devarim? Right, it's all
about what you say, it's not about what you're thinking. If we
make a contract and I say, oh well what I really thinking
was that if the stock would go up,
you know, by the end of the week then I didn't mean
to sell it. Right, so I'm sorry, you know, so it doesn't
matter what you're thinking, right? גבי ההוא דזבין לנכסיה אדעתא למיסק לארץ
ישראל ובעידנא דזבין לא
אמר. gabi hahu d'zaven l'nichsei ada'ata l'meisik l'eretz yisrael u'v'idna d'zaven lo
amar. Like oh I was only selling it because I was planning
on making עליה. aliyah. Since that didn't work out I didn't want
to sell it. Tough luck, you didn't say it. So it doesn't
matter what you're thinking, it matters what you said. התם אינו טועה
בדיבורו. hasam eino toeh bidiburo. So there you go, that plays into
a discussion we were having before. There it wasn't a mistake. You
knew what you were thinking, but you didn't say it. אבל הכא
דברים שבלב הם ומה שהוציא בפיו אינו כלום לפי שטעה בדיבורו aval
hacha devarim shebalev heim u'mah shehotzi befiv eino klum l'fi sheta'ah bidiburo
or you said the other half too late.
But meaning here the point is what you said was not what
you were intending to say. Okay, so there it's easier to throw
out what you said. You misspoke, right? דברים שבלב אינם דברים devarim
shebalev einam devarim
according to תוספות Tosafot is that there was a condition you wanted
to say which you didn't say. You didn't say what needed to
be said. In that case I'm sorry, you didn't say it, we
can't give any credit to what you were thinking and not saying.
But if you misspoke, you said something different from what you were
thinking, then we could sort of dismiss what you had said. And
that's what תוספות Tosafot says. There by the way is another reason
why if there's a difference between these cases, and this is the
point that תוספות ריד Tosafot Rid makes, it's also emerges from the
רמב"ם Rambam and it's very important, is is it a two-sided act
or a one-sided act? When I am making—although it's true the קרבן
korban sort of affects other people—but if I'm making a נדר, neder,
I'm not going to go into this house. If I'm saying this
is תרומה, trumah, this is an עולה, olah, if
I'm saying this is לשם בעלים. l'shem ba'alim. That is basically about
between me and God, right? It's defining the status of the קרבן,
korban, it's creating a נדר, neder, it's not something that is with
another person directly involved. If we're having a business transaction, there's no
way we can take into account what you're thinking, right? If it's
not out there and stated and objective and accessible, you can't hold
the other party bound by it. So in a type of a
two-sided transaction if it's not being said it's completely ignored. Whereas in
a one-sided transaction where it's a question of what is the halakhic
status of this, then it might be we're willing to consider what
you were thinking as well. Okay so let's take a look now
at the next משנה. mishna. Now we switch gears a little bit
to I think a somewhat easier discussion. השוחט את הפסח על החמץ.
hashochet et hapesach al hachametz. So now we're talking about, now we
talked about bad thoughts by your thing and you'll see a little
bit how that discussion had to proceed this. Now we're talking about
a unique issue about פסח, pesach, which is the prohibition of לא
תשחט על חמץ דם זבחי. lo tishchat al chametz dam zivchi. You
can't שחט shacht the פסח pesach with חמץ chametz around. Now it
does say, doesn't say פסח, pesach, it says דם זבחי. dam zivchi.
So actually as we'll see in this משנה, mishna, according to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, even another קרבן korban שחט shachted during פסח, pesach,
if you own חמץ chametz is לא תשחט על חמץ דם זבחי.
lo tishchat al chametz dam zivchi. He understands it to mean when
חמץ chametz is prohibited starting from the fourteenth in the afternoon until
the end. of פסח, Pesach, you cannot be שחט—if shechting you own
חמץ chametz and you're שחט shechting a קרבן, korban, that's another violation
in addition to the violation of owning חמץ. chametz. The other חכמים
chakhamim disagree and they say it's only a prohibition of שחט shechting
a קרבן פסח korban Pesach when you're owning חמץ. chametz. So that's
one issue, what does it refer to? And the other question is,
what does it mean על חמץ? al chametz? Who has the חמץ?
chametz? Okay, so let's take a look at this משנה. mishna. השוחט
את הפסח על החמץ עובר בלא תעשה. Hashochet et hapesach al hachametz
over belo taaseh. Okay, so that's rephrasing the פסוק. pasuk. Now let's
talk about it. רבי יהודה אומר: Rabbi Yehuda omer: אף התמיד. af
hatamid. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says even if you שחט shecht the
afternoon תמיד tamid on ערב פסח, erev Pesach, it's not limited to
the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. Whether he would say it's during, you
know, during the rest of the חג chag is not clear, but
at least at ערב פסח, erev Pesach, which is the זמן שחיטת
חמץ, zman shchitat chametz, it would apply for the תמיד tamid as
well. It would apply for other קרבנות korbanot as well. The זמן
שחיטת פסח zman shchitat pesach would apply for other קרבנות korbanot as
well.
רבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon omer: now here's what רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says. הפסח בארבעה עשר, Hapesach bearba asar, if you're שחט shechting
the קרבן פסח korban Pesach on the fourteenth, לשמו, lishmo, for the
sake of פסח, Pesach, so it's a כשר kasher פסח, Pesach, חייב,
chayav, then you've transgressed.
If you have חמץ, chametz, right. ושלא לשמו Veshelo lishmo פטור. patur.
If you did שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, and this is why the
other משניות mishnayot had to precede this discussion, then you're exempt, because
what's the status of a פסח Pesach שלא לשמו? shelo lishmo?
It's פסול. pasul. Okay, now, why don't we say, very nice, it's
פסול, pasul, but you still שחט shechted it? You still שחט shechted
פסח על דם זבחי. Pesach al dam zivchi. So here is a
very important other principle of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, we're dealing with
רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon principles on this דף, daf, which is, רבי
שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position is שחיטה שאינה ראויה
לא קריא שחיטה, shchita she'eina reu'ya lo kriya shchita, that לא שמיה
שחיטה, lo shemei shchita, right I translated. Okay, so if the שחיטה
shchita did not have the effect of making the meat permissible or
of making it a good קרבן, korban, if it was an invalidating
שחיטה, shchita, so
in that case, it wasn't a שחיטה. shchita. It was like you
just, you know, like stabbed it. We don't call it an act
of שחיטה. shchita. We don't just say it didn't have the effect
of being מתיר, matir, we don't call it an act of שחיטה.
shchita. So he says you didn't transgress because it wasn't an act
of שחיטה. shchita. פטור. patur. Now, that's חידוש chiddush number one. Moving
on to חידוש chiddush number two.
א קשיא. A kasha. פטור patur from what?
From transgressing the law and getting lashes.
But you still—but you still did something you shouldn't have done.
You owned חמץ, chametz, that's a different conversation, but you're פטור patur
from this לאו. lav.
Owning חמץ chametz means that you can't transgress the שחיטה shchita prohibition.
What? No, no, no. It's not an invalid שחיטה shchita because you
transgressed the לאו, lav, it's invalid because it was שלא לשמו. shelo
lishmo.
Oh, got it.
But because you mentioned that, I'll turn your attention quickly to this
תוספות Tosafot at the bottom. השוחט את הפסח על החמץ עובר בלא
תעשה. Hashochet et hapesach al hachametz over belo taaseh. אומר ריב"א Omer
Riva דפסח כשר. depesach kashar. דהא לא שנה עליו הכתוב לעכב. dehal
lo shina alav hakatuv le'akev. The Torah never said twice if you
do it you can't do it. And we know by קדשים kodashim
if it doesn't say it twice, it doesn't really mean—no, I don't
mean that—but if it doesn't say it twice, it doesn't invalidate. ובתוספתא
דמכילתא תניא בהדיא: Ub'tosefta d'Mechilta tanyi behedya: השוחט את הפסח על החמץ
בי"ד Hashochet et hapesach al hachametz be-yud-daled עובר בלא תעשה, over belo
taaseh, והפסח עצמו כשר, vehapesach atzmo kashar, ויוצא בו ידי חובתו בפסח.
veyotzei bo yedei chovato bapesach. So you could transgress לא תשחט על
חמץ דם זבחי, lo tishchat al chametz dam zivchi, you could have
חמץ chametz in your house, but you're still יוצא yotzei your מצוה
mitzvah of eating the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. Okay, so that is—so
the פסח—this Pesach transgression does not make the פסח Pesach invalid. But
if you did it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, and you invalidated the
פסח, Pesach, then according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon it's not an
act of שחיטה shchita and you did not transgress.
One is an issue of קרבן korban and one is an issue
of פסח. Pesach.
Basically, yeah. Okay. ושאר כל הזבחים. Veshar kol hazvachim. Now, we had
said before תמיד, tamid, he's going to expand it and say other
קרבנות korbanot as well and throughout the חג chag as well you
can transgress. בין לשמן בין שלא לשמן, Bein lishmen bein shelo lishmen,
if it was ערב פסח, erev Pesach, whether it was לשמו lishmo
or שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, and even if it was כשר, kasher,
פטור, patur, you're exempt, because he understands that on ערב פסח, erev
Pesach, as opposed to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, he thinks on ערב
פסח erev Pesach you can only transgress with the קרבן פסח. korban
Pesach. ערב פסח erev Pesach is the time of קרבן פסח, korban
Pesach, you can only transgress this with the קרבן פסח korban Pesach
not with other things. ובמועד, Uvemoed, but over יום טוב Yom Tov
and חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, then, where the other קרבנות korbanot are
relevant, לשמו lishmo פטור, patur, שלא לשמו shelo lishmo חייב. chayav. If
you do the קרבן פסח korban Pesach לשמו, lishmo, you're exempt. Why?
What's the הלכה halacha if you שחט shecht a קרבן פסח korban
Pesach on the fifteenth of ניסן? Nisan? It's a—yes, but if you
שחט shecht it לשם פסח, leshem pesach, it's פסול. pasul. To make
it a שלמים, shlamim, right, you have to do it שלא לשמו.
shelo lishmo. So if you're שחט, shechting* it לשם פסח *leshem pesach,
it is פסול. pasul. שלא לשמו, Shelo lishmo, which is when you
made it into a שלמים, shlamim, then it's a כשר שלמים, kasher
shlamim, and then חייב, chayav, because you're חייב chayav for other קרבנות
korbanot on פסח Pesach as well. ושאר כל הזבחים, Veshar kol hazvachim,
all the other קרבנות, korbanot, בין לשמן בין שלא לשמן, bein lishmen
bein shelo lishmen, whether you do it לשמו lishmo or שלא לשמו,
shelo lishmo, חייב. chayav. Why? Because what's the הלכה? halacha? All קרבנות
korbanot that you שחט shecht שלא לשמו shelo lishmo are כשר, kasher,
just doesn't count for the בעלים. ba'alim. So it was a כשר
שחיטה, kasher shchita, and therefore you transgressed, because according to him you
transgress לא תשחט על חמץ דם זבחי, lo tishchat al chametz dam
zivchi, any
זבח. zevach. Fourteenth is designated just for קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, but
the rest of the time any כשר קרבן Kasher Korban is going
to be transgressed if it happens on פסח Pesach and you own
חמץ. Chametz. חוץ מן החטאת ששחטו שלא לשמה, Chutz min hachatat sheshachto
shelo lishmah, except for חטאת Chatat because if that's שלא לשמה, Shelo
Lishmah, it's invalid. Okay, now it is true by the way that
a פסח Pesach after the fourteenth is considered to be automatically standing
for שלמים Shelamim because it can no longer be used, it's past
its time and it can't be used for next פסח, Pesach, but
if you explicitly do it לשמה, Lishmah, you force it back into
that box of being a פסח Pesach and you invalidate it.
Yes. I usually like רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's opinions because he has
inclusivity of the פסוקים, Pesukim, but in this one I just don't
see it. It says זבחי Zivchi which seems to me to suggest
one of the specific ones, to דם זבחי. Dam Zivchi. דם זבחי
Dam Zivchi would mean any of them. זבחי Zivchi would specifically talking
about the פסח, Pesach, right? Should mean... that's the משמעות דקרא. Mashmaut
Dekra. I hear you, I hear you.
Okay, let's see what the גמרא Gemara does to unpack this. תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
Who owns the חמץ? Chametz?
That's what the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss.
So the גמרא, Gemara, so the משנה Mishnah is hyper-focused on the
קרבן Korban issue about לשמה, Lishmah, שלא לשמה, Shelo Lishmah, פסח, Pesach,
שאר קרבנות. She'ar Korbanot. The גמרא Gemara with at the... the אמוראים,
Amoraim, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan talk about sort of the other aspects about this
לאו. Lav. So let's take a look. אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש,
Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, לעולם אינו חייב, Le'olam eino chayav, you
don't transgress, עד
שהחמץ לשוחט, Ad shehachametz lashochet, either the שוחט Shochet owns the חמץ,
Chametz, או לזורק. O lazorek.
והשוחט Vehashochet is the כהן.
Kohen. It could be... it could be an owner. I know, but
in standard cases it's the כהן. Kohen. Okay, it could be anyone,
but anyway, either the שוחט Shochet או לזורק. O lazorek. Now that's
interesting. Although it says לא תשחט על חמץ דם זבחי Lo Tishchat
Al Chametz Dam Zivchi and you only transgress when you're שוחט, Shochet,
the end of the פסוק Pasuk says, like, לא תשחט על חמץ
דם זבחי ולא ילין לבקר זבח חג הפסח, Lo tishchat al chametz
dam zivchi velo yalin laboker zevach chag hapessach, where does it say?
Somewhere says there... yeah, that says only don't let it stay over,
but it also says ודם זבחיך ישפך. Vedam zvachecha yishapech.
Is that in that same...?
על מזבח ה' אלוהיך
והבשר תאכל.
Al mizbeach Hashem
Elokecha vehabassar tochal.
Somewhere... that's somewhere else. Anyway, so from somewhere else, based on the
פסוק Pasuk of ודם זבחיך, Vedam zvachecha, maybe the זבחי זבחיך, Zivchi
Zvachecha, we learn... רש"י Rashi refers to a מכילתא Mechilta that we
learn that you also transgress if you do זריקת הדם, Zrikat Hadam,
which is quite interesting, which is nowhere clear in the פסוקים. Pesukim.
Okay, או לאחד מבני חבורה, O leachad mivnei chaburah, or one of
the owners has חמץ. Chametz. Now, but the owners don't transgress. The
only person that transgresses is the one who does the שחיטה. Shechitah.
So that... you have to be clear. First of all, we include
זריקה. Zriaka. So if you do the שחיטה Shechitah or the זריקה
Zriaka with חמץ, Chametz, the one who does the act of שחיטה
Shechitah or זריקה Zriaka transgresses if any one of those people own
the... own חמץ. Chametz. Okay? So but you understand? So you don't
have to be the person owning חמץ, Chametz, and if you own
חמץ, Chametz, you don't necessarily... you don't transgress. You only transgress if
you're the person, I mean, transgress owning חמץ, Chametz, but you don't
transgress... you only transgress if you're the person doing שחיטה Shechitah and
if someone of the group or you own חמץ. Chametz.
Including the שוגג, Shogeg, if... the שוחט Shochet did not know that
I own חמץ. Chametz.
Yes, and that's a good point, right?
What does... everybody?
Right.
What does the כהן Kohen know about what's people... I know. So
he could be total... it would be more of an אנוס Anus
than a שוגג, Shogeg, exactly. I mean... אנוס. Anus. Yeah, that's a
good question. How would you say you're... you're over באונס Be'oness if
you have no... it's a good question, right?
Is he supposed to ask? Does anybody have חמץ?
Chametz? I don't know. Okay, let's keep on going. ועד שיהא עמו
בעזרה. Ve'ad sheyehei imo ba'azarah. Now that maybe addresses the אנוס Anus
part a little bit. The חמץ Chametz has to be in the
עזרה. Azarah.
So because it's לא תשחט על חמץ, Lo Tishchat Al Chametz, the
שחיטה Shechitah has to be on the חמץ. Chametz. So the על
Al means two things: A, it has to be sort of conceptually
related to it. It has to be owned by a member of
the group or by the שוחט. Shochet. And B, it has to
be physically connected to it. It has to be... it has to
be in the עזרה. Azarah. No, you could think of food, just
can't be חמץ. Chametz. Which עזרה? Azarah? The...
oh, the עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, not the עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim.
We're always talking about where the action is going on. No, no,
no. עזרת...... Ezrat... it doesn't matter. הלכתית Halachically it's basically the same.
Why isn't it עזרת נשים? Ezrat Nashim? Why isn't it the women's...?
Yeah,
they... the story, they bring it, but the
מעשה שחיטה, Ma'aseh Shechitah, the מעשה Ma'aseh of the עבודות Avodot are
done in the... in the עזרת ישראל Ezrat Yisrael and that... that's
what we're talking about. Were they? Yes. But we're talking about the
עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, אף על
פי שאינו עמו בעזרה, Af al pi she'eino imo ba'azarah, even if
it's not there with you in the עזרה. Azarah. So במאי קמיפלגי,
Bemai kamiflagi, what do they debate? אילימא בעל בסמוך קמיפלגי. Elima be'al
besamuch kamiflagi. When the תורה Torah says על, Al, how much does
it mean it has to be really geographically, you know, nearby? רבי
שמעון בן לקיש סבר על בסמוך. Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish savar al
besamuch. If it says על חמץ, Al Chametz, it means it has
to be physically nearby. רבי יוחנן סבר לא בעינן על בסמוך. Rabbi
Yochanan savar lo beinan al besamuch. It doesn't mean physically, it means
it's connected to it. So a person of the חבורה Chaburah owns
it, it's connected to it. So the גמרא Gemara says והא איפליגו
בה חדא זימנא, Veha ifligu bah chada zimna, but they already debated
this, didn't they? In a different context. השוחט תודה לפנים ולחמה לחוץ.
Hashochet todah lifnim velachmah lachutz. So when you שחט Shachet תודה, Todah,
the לחם Lechem that comes with the תודה Todah gets sanctified. Actually
gets to a full level. It's a partial level of sanctity, gets
to a full level. And we learn it because it says the
פסוק Pasuk says by the לחם, Lechem, what's the פסוק? Pasuk? Actually
it's in a פסוק *pasuk*. It says על al זבח zevach התודה
חלות חלות לחם *al zevach hatoda chalos chalos lechem* what חלות
לחם חמץ chametz יקריב
קרבנו *chalos lechem chametz yakriv korbano* על al זבח התודה *al zevach
hatoda*. Anyway so there's an על *al* connecting the bread to the
Toda. So do they have to be physically nearby for the שחיטה
shechitah, *shechita* of the Toda because we say the slaughtering of the
Toda sanctifies the bread because they're connected? Do they have to be
physically nearby? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says חוץ לחומה *chutz lachoma*
if it's outside the wall לא קידש הלחם *lo kidesh halechem*. מאי
חוץ לחומה *mai chutz lachoma*? What does it mean outside the wall
that it doesn't work? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* אומר *omeir*
חוץ לחומה בית פאגי *chutz lachoma Beit Pagi*. Outside the wall of
בית פאגי *Beit Pagi* which presumably means the wall of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*.
Okay that it's outside ירושלים *Yerushalayim* then it's really considered not connected
because because the bread is פסול *pasul* outside of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. You
eat the Toda and you eat the bread in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So
if it's out of ירושלים *Yerushalayim* then it's totally disconnected. אבל חוץ
לחומת עזרה Azarah. *aval chutz lechomat azara* if it's just out of
the עזרה Azarah. *azara* not where the קרבן korban *korban* is קדיש
*kadish* it's holy. ובלא בעינן על בסמוך *u'vela bainan al basamuch* על
*al* does not have to mean that it has to be next
nearby. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* אומר *omeir* אפילו חוץ לחומת
עזרה Azarah לא קדיש *afilu chutz lechomat azara lo kadish*. Even outside
of the עזרה Azarah. *azara* one step outside the עזרה Azarah *azara*
it's not sanctified. אלמא בעינן על בסמוך *alma bainan al basamuch* for
על *al* means physically nearby. So therefore that can't be... why are
they debating about that if we already know they've debated about it?
Now okay you know some people they might be having their same
debate in different contexts which is what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will
say. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to explore is that the
debate whether על *al* means physically nearby? We know they debate that.
אלא מיהא *ela miha* they're debating a different point when it's not
in the עזרה Azarah. *azara*. דהתראת ספק קמיפלגי *de'hatra'at safeik kamifligi*. A
doubtful התראה *hatraa* and this gets to the issue about like how
does how does the כהן Kohen *kohein* know? Right because so you're
going to warn the כהן Kohen *kohein* don't שחט shecht *shacht*! One
of the owners has חמץ chametz, *chametz*. Don't שחט shecht *shacht*! Right?
And that's what you're going to say. ובהא נמי פליגי בחדא זימנא
*u'veha nami pligi bechada zimna*. And what would be the התראת ספק
*hatra'at safeik*? So you say don't שחט Shecht *shacht* I know ראובן
*Reuven* who owns that קרבן korban *korban* has חמץ chametz *chametz*. Now
it's his חמץ chametz, *chametz* is somewhere else then how do you
know it's still around? How do you know he still owns it?
And maybe the כהן Kohen *kohein* doesn't believe you. Maybe the כהן
Kohen *kohein* thinks I don't think he owns חמץ chametz *chametz* you're
just telling me? I've no reason to think that's true. I don't
see any חמץ chametz *chametz* here. So if it's not physically present
for the כהן *kohein* to see so then it's not just about
being in the עזרה Azarah *azara* it's about the כהן *kohein* seeing
it and being aware of it. And going back to ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish. *Reish Lakish* in theory if ראובן *Reuven* was standing in
the עזרת נשים *ezrat nashim* holding his חמץ chametz *chametz* and you
could see him there it would also be relevant. Okay so it's
a question about the כהן *kohein* being aware of it. Okay but
if that's the debate so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says בהא נמי
פליגי בחדא זימנא *beha nami pligi bechada zimna*. We already know that's
a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan וריש לקיש *Rabbi Yochanan u'Reish
Lakish* דאיתמר *de'itmar* שבועה שאוכל כיכר זו היום *shvua she'ocheil kikar zu
hayom*. A person takes an oath that I'll eat this loaf of
bread today. ועבר היום ולא אכלה *ve'avar hayom velo achla*. And the
day went by he didn't eat it. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan וריש
לקיש *Rabbi Yochanan u'Reish Lakish* דאמרי תרווייהו *de'amri tarvaihu* they both say
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan וריש לקיש *Rabbi Yochanan u'Reish Lakish* אינו לוקה
*eino lokei*. He doesn't get lashes. But they say this for different
reasons. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר אינו לוקה *Rabbi Yochanan amar eino
lokei* he doesn't get lashes משום דהוי ליה לאו שאין בו מעשה
*mishum de'havai lei lav she'ein bo ma'aseh*. Because he didn't do an
act he just passively didn't eat. וכל לאו שאין בו מעשה אין
לוקין עליו *vechol lav she'ein bo ma'aseh ein lokin alav*. Any transgression
without an act you don't get lashes. אבל התראת ספק *aval hatra'at
safeik* the fact that it was a doubtful warning שמה התראה *shma
hatraa*. That would still be a legitimate warning and you need the
warning to get lashes. Why is it a doubtful warning? Because I
would say to you: you better eat that loaf of bread if
you don't eat it you're going to get you know you're going
to get lashes. But at that moment when I'm ignoring you I
don't know that I'm necessarily going to transgress. We're only going to
find out that I'm going to transgress if I keep on not
eating it for the rest of the day.
Okay so we still got both over.
What? You're over you transgressed the
לאו *lav* you
don't get מלקות *malkos*. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish אמר אינו לוקה *Reish
Lakish amar eino lokei*. You don't get lashes for a different reason.
משום דהוי ליה התראת ספק *mishum de'havai lei hatra'at safeik*. It's a
doubtful warning meaning I the one you're warning am in doubt about
it. והתראת ספק לאו שמה התראה *ve'hatra'at safeik lav shma hatraa* and
it's not legitimate. So here too maybe the debate is I'm telling
the כהן *kohein* don't שחט *shacht* you're going to be over and
the כהן *kohein* doubts what I'm saying is true because he doesn't
see the חמץ chametz. *chametz*. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish*
says I can't give you lashes and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rabbi
Yochanan* says I can still give you lashes if it turns out
he was warned and the guy had חמץ chametz, *chametz* even if
the כהן *kohein* didn't know about it and was doubting it but
he was warned and therefore he'll get lashes. אבל לאו שאין בו
מעשה לא לקין עליו *aval lav she'ein bo ma'aseh lo lakin alav*...
I'm sorry that's the end of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. *Reish Lakish*'s
statement. For being passive I would give you lashes but I'm not
giving you lashes because you're in doubt about whether the warning is
really you know whether you're really going to transgress even though you've
been warned.
So anyway but רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*'s position is true
for any התראה *hatraa* right? You don't know... you don't know if
the person...
No. If I say don't make that fire or you'll be מחלל
שבת *mechaleil Shabbos* what's your doubt? You've been told it's חילול שבת
*chilul Shabbos* you go ahead you make the fire there's no doubt
that you're transgressing in this act. But in this case the כהן
*kohein* either doubts that the guy has חמץ chametz. *chametz* or when
I ignore you and don't eat the loaf of bread I doubt
that I'll transgress. grab because I may, I'm thinking maybe I'll eat
it later.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, וצריכא. u-tzricha. So the
גמרא Gemara says, לעולם ב"על סמוך" מיפלגו, le'olam be-al samuch mipalgu, which
is what it sounds like. They're really debating that old debate of
whether על means physically nearby, but they needed to debate it in
two places: in the case of the תודה todah and the bread,
and the case of the חמץ chametz, and the פסח. Pesach. וצריכא,
u-tzricha, and you need to say both cases. דאי איפלגו לעניין חמץ,
de-i iflgu le-inyan chametz, had they just debated the חמץ, chametz. הוה
אמינא בהא, hava amina be-ha, who דקאמר de-ka'amar רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
דלא בעינן על סמוך, de-lo be'inan al samuch, that's where רבי יוחנן
says that על doesn't have to mean nearby as long as it's
connected to it, even if the חמץ chametz? isn't in the
עזרה. Azarah. משום דאיסורא הוא, mishum de-issura hu, it's a transgression, you
know? And therefore we'll see what the איסור issur is in context.
דכל היכא דאיתא איתא, de-kol heicha de-ita ita, wherever there's חמץ, chametz,
it's a problem. If there's חמץ chametz somehow connected, even if it's
not physically there, it creates a problem. אבל לעניין מקדש לחם, aval
le-inyan mekadesh lechem, when it comes to the issue of sanctifying the
bread—no, מקדש—when mekadesh it comes to the issue of sanctifying the bread,
לא קדוש אלא בפנים, lo kadosh ella bifnim, then the bread has
to be on the inside. Why?
Well, we'll see in a minute. אימא מודה ליה לריש לקיש, eima
modeh lei le-Reish Lakish, there there's an argument if the bread wants
to get the sanctity through the שחיטה, shechitah, it has to be
in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to get the sanctity. The גמרא
Gemara will spell that out in a minute. Maybe there he would
agree to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that the bread has to be
in the עזרה. Azarah. דבעינן על סמוך, de-be'inan al samuch, I might
agree. דאי איכא גוואי קדיש, de-i ika gavai kadish, and now it
says if it's inside it would be sanctified, אי לאו לא קדיש,
i lav lo kadish, if it's out of the עזרה Azarah. it
would not be sanctified. מדידהוה ככלי שרת, mideihavei ke-kli shareis, just like
by a כלי שרת. kli shareis. What does it mean just like
by a כלי שרת? kli shareis? רש״י Rashi says when you put
something in a כלי שרת, kli shareis, it sanctifies the thing that's
put into it. But it has to be put into it. So
רש״י Rashi in a way thinks of the whole בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash as a type of כלי שרת, kli shareis, you know, or
a כלי שרת kli shareis as a mini בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
But things that are in it, you know, they are more able
to be sanctified, especially through this act of שחיטה, shechitah this other
עבודה avodah that's being done, than things that are outside of it.
תוספות Tosafos says it a little different, a little more technical point.
He says the כלי שרת's kli shareis ability to sanctify things that
are put into it only works when the כלי שרת kli shareis
is in the עזרה. Azarah. If the כלי שרת kli shareis is
out of the עזרה Azarah it doesn't have that power. So here
too, the שחיטה shechitah, of the זבח's ability to sanctify the bread
would only be when the bread is in the עזרה. Azarah, So
there you could say for other reasons it has to be in
the עזרה Azarah and maybe he agrees to ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish,
וצריכא, u-tzricha, so therefore he had to tell you that even there
he disagrees with ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, and it could be out
of the עזרה. Azarah. ואי אשמעינן לעניין מקדש לחם, ve-i ashmeinan le-inyan
mekadesh lechem, had they just debated the case of the bread, הוה
אמינא בהא קאמר ריש
לקיש, hava amina be-ha ka'amar Reish Lakish, that's where—only in the case
of the bread and the תודה todah does ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
insist it be in the עזרה. Azarah דבעינן על סמוך, de-be'inan al
samuch, you need it to be nearby. דאי איכא גוואי קדיש אי
לאו לא קדיש, de-i ika gavai kadish i lav lo kadish, only
if it's inside is it sanctified, not if it's outside. אבל לעניין
חמץ, aval le-inyan chametz, maybe when it comes to a transgression and
it's just about owning and being connected to it, מודה ליה לרבי
יוחנן, modeh lei le-Rabbi Yochanan, maybe he would agree to רבי יוחנן
דלא בעינן על סמוך, de-lo be'inan al samuch, that it didn't have
to be physically nearby. דאיסורא הוא, de-issura hu, it's about a prohibition,
a transgression, וכל היכא דאיתא איתא, ve-kol heicha de-ita ita, wherever it
is, you've transgressed. וצריכא, u-tzricha, so you need to say both. So
now we have a very beautiful articulation of this debate of רבי
יוחנן and ריש לקיש. על חמץ, al chametz, does it mean physically
nearby? They debate it, ריש לקיש says yes, רבי יוחנן says no.
And the גמרא Gemara points out that even in another place they
had that debate, but there there would be more reason to say
it would have to be physically nearby because it's about an act
of sanctifying and would have to be in the עזרה. But here
maybe it's about owning and transgressing and it's connected—the connecting the חמץ
chametz? to it, but not about sanctifying—and therefore, at least according to
רבי יוחנן, you don't have to have it in the עזרה. Both
do agree though, whether it's in the עזרה or not, that you
also need to have the more conceptual connection, not just the physical
proximity. Right? If I have חמץ chametz, in the עזרה, it doesn't
mean all of you guys who are bringing your פסח Pesach are
transgressed. The physical proximity is not sufficient. It might be necessary according
to ריש לקיש, but it's not sufficient. What they all agree that
you need is that it be owned either by the שוחט shochet
or by the members of the חבורה. chaburah. But again, the members
of the חבורה chaburah don't transgress, only the שוחט shochet transgresses.
And the פסח Pesach is still good. Okay, now, בעי מיניה רב
אושעיא מרבי אמי, ba'ei minei Rav Oshaya me-Rabbi Ami, רב אושעיא Rav
Oshaya asked רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya didn't hear
of this debate of רבי יוחנן and ריש לקיש, or maybe he
wanted to re-explore it and he revisited this question of who owns
the חמץ. chametz. אין לו לשוחט ויש לו לאחד מבני החבורה מהו?
ein lo la-shochet ve-yesh lo le-achad mi-benei ha-chaburah mahu?
Let's say the שוחט shochet doesn't have חמץ, chametz, but one of
the members of the group does. We already know what רבי יוחנן
and ריש לקיש say about this, but he wanted to know. Is
it clear that you transgress? אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back
to him, מי כתיב לא תשחט על חמצך? mi ksiv lo tishchat
al chamtzecha? It doesn't say "don't slaughter on your חמץ." chametz? לא
תשחט על חמץ כתיב. lo tishchat al chametz ksiv. Don't slaughter, it
shouldn't be with חמץ, chametz somehow connected to the חמץ. chametz אמר
ליה, amar lei, he said to him, אי הכי אפילו אחד בסוף
העולם נמי? i hachi afilu echad bi-sof ha-olam nami? So if that's
true, so maybe even if it's someone in the world, somebody owns
חמץ? chametz, Now, רש״י Rashi says somebody in... which isn't exactly בסוף
העולם. besof haolam. Okay, but in a חבורה? Chaburah?
No, no, but that's his question. If it doesn't—what forces it—if it
doesn't have to be yours, why limit it to the חבורה's? Chaburah
The way רש״י Rashi understands the question, maybe
if somebody in the
עזרה has
חמץ, chametz, it's על חמץ. al chametz. Okay, I mean if you
say it that way, it's easier to understand. Okay, maybe it's enough
that there's חמץ chametz in the עזרה. אמר ליה, amar lei, אמרה
קרא, amrah krah, לא תשחט, lo tishchat, לא תשחט ולא ילין. lo
tishchat velo yalin. לא תשחט lo tishchat הסמיכו הכתוב hismicho hakatuv ולא
ילין חלב חגי עד בוקר. velo yalin chelev chagi ad boker. לא
תשחט על חמץ, lo tishchat al chametz, who says—who is prohibited to
be שחט-ing on חמץ? chametz הנך דקיימי עליה משום לא ילין, hanach
dekayami alei mishum lo yalin, those that will have to worry about
being—about making it sleep overnight, meaning—no, but yeah, but instead of saying
about this קרבן korban having to worry overnight. So the לא תשחט
על חמץ lo tishchat al chametz is, you know, those that are
relate to the קרבן korban and therefore we can also tell them
ולא ילין חלב חגי עד בוקר. velo yalin chelev chagi ad boker.
I know, you could have obviously said otherwise. Anyway, so that's how
we get this idea that it has to be the owners, or
the person that's שחט-ing here, clearly then he's connecting it. And whether
it also has to be in the עזרה is debatable. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav
Papa, הלכך, hilkach, by the way, it's worth pointing out that the
כהן isn't necessarily in the—in the relating to the בל ילין, bal
yalin, because it's—he's not eating that meat, he's not necessarily part of
that חבורה, Chaburah, but if he—if the שוחט shochet has the חמץ,
chametz, that's clearly included. In addition, if anybody who's in the category
of לא ילין lo yalin has it, that also makes the שוחט
shochet transgress. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, הלכך, hilkach, if that's
it, it's about לא ילין, lo yalin, I'm going to say something
else. כהן המקטיר את החלב Kohen hamaktir et hachelev עובר בלא תעשה.
over belo taaseh. Let's say the כהן who's burning the fat of
a קרבן פסח korban Pesach has חמץ. chametz, He transgresses a לא
תעשה. lo taaseh. Why? Or maybe one of the בני חבורה bnei
Chaburah has חמץ, chametz but he transgresses, הואיל וישנו בכלל הלנת אימורין,
hoil veyeshno bichlal halanat imurin,
because בל ילין bal yalin applies to him in the sense that
he can't let the fat not be burned on the מזבח, mizbeach,
he can't let the fat wait over till the next day. So
therefore he's also included. Of course the גמרא Gemara is a bit
of a—it's a big jump. שחט it? No, לא ילין lo yalin
means don't let the meat wait.
And what does that have to do with חמץ?
Because it's connected. לא תשחט על חמץ דם זבחי ולא ילין
חלב חגי עד בוקר.
lo tishchat al chametz dam zivchi velo yalin
chelev
chagi ad boker.
I understand, but the גמרא gemara is saying something about the juxtaposition.
That if you're in the category of לא ילין, lo yalin, you're
in the category of לא תשחט. lo tishchat. So but the גמרא
gemara did a big jump. We should appreciate the jump that the
גמרא did here because the גמרא has been using לא ילין lo
yalin to indicate whose ownership of חמץ is relevant. The people who
are in לא ילין, lo yalin, their ownership of חמץ is relevant.
The jump that we just did is to say that even a
completely different act, not only שחיטה, shechitah. not only זריקה, zrikah, which
is also somehow included as רש״י Rashi indicates, but now a new
act that is—that we've never heard of before is that was this
transgression. This transgression is לא תשחט. lo tishchat. We're going to say
that you also transgress by doing הקטרת אימורין. haktarat imurin. Why? Because
you are related to this קרבן by בל ילין, bal yalin, so
therefore your act of הקטרת אימורין haktarat imurin is also a transgression.
It's like, so what? I mean, the תורה Torah says לא תשחט,
lo tishchat, so it's really a—it's an amazing jump that is being
done here to include not only the ownership of the חמץ, you
know, maybe if you would have said the כהן who's מקטיר maktir
the אימורין, imurin, if he owns חמץ, that somehow makes the שוחט
shochet transgress—of course that wouldn't work retroactively, but, you know, because you
don't know who that is yet. But again, he's not talking about
ownership. Right, I understand. But doing it on the basis of לא
ילין, lo yalin, it was totally fine when לא ילין lo yalin
indicated whose ownership was relevant. But now he's using it to say
whose act—because we know
this כהן is going to do the הקטרת אימורין haktarat imurin and
I'm שוחט, shochet, whatever.
Yeah, but how do you know? Anyway, let's take a look. We'll
just do one more line where the גמרא supports that. תניא כוותיה
דרב פפא, tanya kivatei deRav Papa, we taught a ברייתא braita like
רב פפא. Rav Papa. השוחט את הפסח על החמץ hashochet et haPesach
al hachametz עובר בלא תעשה. over belo taaseh. אימתי? eimatai? When is
this true? בזמן שהוא לשוחט או לזורק או לאחד מבני חבורה. bizman
shehu lashochet o lazorek o leachad mibnei chaburah. Now we're also saying
that a relevant owner is also the one who's doing זריקת הדם.
zrikat hadam. Okay, because we said that זריקה zrikah is also an
act that you can transgress. Of course, it doesn't mean that if
the זורק zorek has חמץ the שוחט shochet is עובר. over. So
it's not so clear. Presumably if the זורק zorek has חמץ the
זורק zorek is עובר. over. Anyway, if any of these people have
חמץ, the שוחט shochet or the
זורק zorek עובר בלא תעשה. over belo taaseh. אימתי? eimatai? When is
this true? I'm—I just read that. היה לאחד בסוף העולם, hayah leachad
besof haolam, אין זקוק לו. ein zakuk lo. Some other stranger has
חמץ, not your problem.
ואחד השוחט ואחד הזורק ואחד המקטיר חייב. veechad hashochet veechad hazorek veechad
hamaktir chayav. And by the way, what act are you חייב chayav
for? שחיטה. shechita, זריקה zrika and הקטרת אימורים haktaras emurim are acts
you could be חייב chayav for.
אבל המולק את העוף בארבעה עשר אינו עובר בלא כלום. aval hamolek
es ha'of bearba'ah asar eino over belo klum. And so if you
do מליקה melika and on חמץ you're not עובר. over. Now, the
way it's phrased, you would think the reason you're not עובר over
if you bring an עוף of and do מליקה melika is because
it's not an act of שחיטה, shechita, right? But as we'll see
later, the גמרא's going to assume and רש״י Rashi sort of says
here, no, the reason you're not עובר over is because on ערב
פסח erev pesach the only thing you're עובר over for is a
קרבן פסח. korban pesach. So therefore, if you're doing מליקה, melika, it's
not a קרבן פסח. korban pesach.
Why would you
bring, and other קרבנות korbanos also wouldn't be a problem.
Why would you bring a bird?
Because, because and that's why רש״י Rashi says we're talking about a
bird because you need because birds are very common in מחוסרי כפורים
mechusrei kippurim
in finishing up the טהרה taharah process. So and you would be
bringing this bird even after the תמיד tamid so you could become
טהור tahor so you could eat the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. But
again, the framing makes it sound like it's the act of מליקה's
melika not an act of שחיטה, but the way the גמרא and
רש״י Rashi understand this, it's because that is not the right קרבן
to be עובר over on at this time.